# Dr.-Ing. Florian Kummer

DATE OF BIRTH: July the 14<sup>th</sup>, 1981 PLACE OF BIRTH: Innsbruck, Austria

NATIONALITY: Austria

E-MAIL: kummer@fdy.tu-darmstadt.de,

florian.kummer@outlook.com

PHONE: +49 (0)163 6714857

WORK ADDRESS: FG für Strömungsdynamik, TU Darmstadt

Otto-Berndt-Straße 2

64287 Darmstadt, Germany

HOME ADDRESS: Friedhofstraße 15

64380 Gundernhausen, Germany

# **Professional background**

2015 - now Research group leader at the Chair of Fluid Dynamics (FDY), TU Darmstadt

• responsible for multi-phase research group and software development

2014 - 2015 Visiting Scholar at the Department of Computational and Applied Mathematics (CAAM), Rice University

(CAAIVI), RICE UNIVERSITY

• Reference: Prof. Tim Warburton, tim.warburton@gmail.com

2013 - 2014 Research Associate at Center for Turbulence Research (CTR), Stanford University

• Reference: Prof. Parviz Moin, moin@stanford.edu.

• Reference: Prof. Ali Mani, alimani@stanford.edu.

2006 – 2012 Research Staff at Chair of Fluid Dynamics (FDY), TU Darmstadt

- Postdoctoral researcher (2011 2013), PhD student (2006 2011).
- Successful defense of PhD thesis, with distinction (Nov 2011).
- Associated student at the *Graduate School of Computational Engineering* (2009 2011).

## **Undergraduate education, misc.:**

2000 - 2006 Studies of Technical Mathematics, University of Innsbruck

- Master thesis: *Operator splitting for parabolic PDE's*, chosen subject: computer science.
- Reference: Univ.-Prof. Dr. Alexander Ostermann, alexander.ostermann@uibk.ac.at.

2002 - 2003 Military duty service

1995 - 2000 Federal Secondary College of Engineering, communications engineering branch

### **Awards and distinctions**

2017	Prize of the Adolf Messer Foundation 2017 (Preis der Adolf Messer
	Stiftung), endowed with 50,000 €, http://www.adolf-messer-stiftung.de/
	stiftungspreise/index.php
2013	PhD Award 2013 of the Graduate School CE
2013	GAMM Junior Award 2013/2014.

#### **Publications**

#### **Peer-Reviewed Journals:**

Articles which have been published or officially accepted by publication outlets with scientific quality assurance and book publications.

- [1] Kummer, F., Müller, B., and Utz, T. (2017). Time integration for extended discontinuous Galerkin methods with moving domains. *International Journal for Numerical Methods in Engineering*, 113(5):767–788
- [2] Utz, T. and Kummer, F. (2017). A high-order discontinuous Galerkin method for extension problems. *International Journal for Numerical Methods in Fluids*, 86(8):509–518
- [3] Krause, D. and Kummer, F. (2017). An incompressible immersed boundary solver for moving body flows using a cut cell discontinuous Galerkin method. *Computers & Fluids*, 153:118–129
- [4] Utz, T., Kummer, F., and Oberlack, M. (2017). Interface-preserving level-set reinitialization for DG-FEM. *International Journal for Numerical Methods in Fluids*, 84(4):183–198
- [5] Müller, B., Krämer-Eis, S., Kummer, F., and Oberlack, M. (2017). A high-order discontinuous Galerkin method for compressible flows with immersed boundaries. *International Journal for Numerical Methods in Engineering*, 110(1):3–30
- [6] Kummer, F. (2017). Extended discontinuous Galerkin methods for two-phase flows: the spatial discretization. *International Journal for Numerical Methods in Engineering*, 109(2):259–289
- [7] Klein, B., Müller, B., Kummer, F., and Oberlack, M. (2016). A high-order discontinuous Galerkin solver for low-Mach number flows. *International Journal for Numerical Methods in Fluids*, 81(8):1097–0363
- [8] Kummer, F. and Warburton, T. (2016). Patch-recovery filters for curvature in discontinuous Galerkin based level-set methods. *Communications in Computational Physics*, 19(02):329–353
- [9] Müller, B., Kummer, F., and Oberlack, M. (2013). Highly accurate surface and volume integration on implicit domains by means of moment-fitting. *International Journal for Numerical Methods in Engineering*, 96(8):512–528
- [10] Kummer, F. and Oberlack, M. (2013). An extension of the discontinuous Galerkin method for the singular Poisson equation. *SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing*, 35(2):A603–A622

## Third-party funding

# Successful grant applications:

The following is a list of successful applications for third-party funding, with significant contributions from my side in application and supervision or execution of the project. If not noted otherwise, the principal investigator is Prof. Dr. Martin Oberlack (oberlack@fdy.tu-darmstadt.de).

- Collaborative Research Center 1194, B06: Higher Order Schemes for Direct Numerical Simulation for Wetting and De-Wetting Problems based on Discontinuous Galerkin Methods, 1st funding period (2016 2020).
- **Research Scholarship:** Discontinuous Galerkin methods for incompressible multi-phase flows, Two year funding for a research stay in the U.S., DFG Project-No: KU2719/1-1, **personal responsibility** (2013 2014).
- **Priority Programme 1506, Proj. 8:** Discontinuous Galerkin Simulation of Multiphase flows with Interfacial Equations **two** individual applications for the 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> funding period (2010 2016).
- **DFG Research Grant:** Theoretical, numerical and experimental investigation of droplet-layers on electrically stressed insulator surfaces, 2 years funding (2012 2014).
- Collaborative Research Centre 568, B05: Analysis and modeling of generalized boundary condition for the G-equation. 3<sup>rd</sup> funding period (2007 2011).

### **Invited talks**

- Volkswagen AG, AutoUni Seminar: Extended Discontinuous Galerkin: essentiell Netz-freie Simulationsmethoden für bewegte Geometrien und Mehrphasenströmungen Nov. 2018, Reference: Dr.-Ing. Alexandra Mutzke
- Numerische Simulation, Mathematisches Institut, Universität zu Köln: On the Simulation of Contact Line Dynamics using Sharp-Interface Methods Nov. 2018, Reference: Prof. Gregor Gassner
- SimTech Kolloquium, Cluster of Excellence SimTeCH, University of Stuttgart, Germany: Extended discontinuous Galerkin methods and their application: immersed boundary and multiphase, Jun. 2017, Reference: Prof. Claus-Dieter Munz.
- IRTG Lecture, Transregio 146, TU Darmstadt, Germany: Extended Discontinuous Galerkin Methods for flows on instationary domains: fluid-structure interaction and multiphase, May 2017, Reference: Dr. Giovanni Settanni.
- Numerical Analysis Seminar, Matematikcentrum, Lund Univesity, Sweden: Extended Discontinuous Galerkin Methods for flows on instationary domains: fluid-structure interaction and multiphase, May 2017, Reference: Prof. Phillip Birken.

- CompSE Workshop 2016, Aachen Institute for Advanced Study in Computational Engineering Science (AICES), Germany: Long-term stability-issues in high-order multiphase flow simulations, Jun. 2016, Reference: Prof. Marek Behr
- Center for Turbulence Research Tea Seminar, Stanford University, USA: Discontinuous Galerkin methods for multi-phase flows, Mar. 2013, Reference: Prof. Parviz Moin.
- Center for Turbulence Research Tea Seminar, Stanford University, USA: BoSSS: Bounded Support Spectral Solver, A Generic Discontinuous Galerkin Framework, May 2009, Reference: Prof. Parviz Moin.

Conference talks		
STAB 2018	High-order numerical methods for fluid simulation with dynamic interfaces, 21. DGLR-FAch-Symposium der STAB, <b>Darmstadt</b> , <b>Germany</b> .	
XDMS 2017	On the combination of extended Galerkin methods with mesh adaptation, 13 <sup>th</sup> World Congress on Computational Mechanics, <b>New York</b> , <b>USA</b> .	
APS DFD 2017	High-fidelity droplet and bubble simulations using local enrichment, American Physical Society 70 <sup>th</sup> Annual DFD Meeting, <b>Denver, CO, USA</b> .	
X-DMS 2017	Minisymposium Organizer: High-order embedded methods for static and moving domains, together with Prof. Dominik Schillinger, ECCOMAS thematic conference on eXtended Discretization MethodS, June 2017, Umeå, Sweden.	
X-DMS 2017	The application of classical temporal integration schemes on problems with moving domain, ECCOMAS thematic conference on eXtended Discretization MethodS, June 2017, Umeå, Sweden.	
FEF 2017	Galerkin Methods for fluid dynamical problems with dynamic boundaries: multiphase flows, IACM 19 <sup>th</sup> International Conference on Finite Elements in Flow Problems, <b>Rome, Italy</b> .	
ECCOMAS 2016	High-order discretizations for multiphase flow: choice of basis, preconditioning and temporal discretization, 7 <sup>th</sup> European congress on computational methods in applies sciences and engineering, <b>Crete Island, Greece</b> .	
APS DFD 2015	High-order accurate multi-phase simulations: building blocks and what's tricky about them, American Physical Society 68 <sup>th</sup> Annual DFD Meeting, <b>Boston, MA, USA</b> .	
X-DMS 2015	<b>Minisymposium Organizer:</b> <i>Higher order eXtended discretization methods</i> , together with Björn Müller, TU Darmstadt, ECCOMAS thematic conference on eXtended Discretization MethodS, <b>Ferrara</b> , <b>Italy</b> .	
HONOM 2015	High order discretizations for two-phase flow: spatial discretization, curvature evaluation and solver strategies, European Workshop on High Order Nonlinear Numerical Methods, <b>Trient, Italy</b> .	
APS DFD 2013	Discontinuous Galerkin methods for multi-phase flows, American Physical Society 66 <sup>th</sup> Annual DFD Meeting, <b>Pittsburgh, PA, USA</b> .	
ECCOMAS 2012	An extended discontinuous Galerkin method for multiphase flows, 6 <sup>th</sup> European congress on computational methods in applies sciences and engineering, <b>Wien, Austria</b> .	

ICNMMF 2012	An Extension to the Discontinuous Galerkin Method, Aiming on Multiphase Problems, International Conference on Numerical methods in Multiphase Flows Pennsylvania State University, University Park, PA, USA.
ICCE 2011	The Extended Discontinuous Galerkin (XDG) method for discontinuous linear PDE's, 2 <sup>nd</sup> International Conference on Computational Engineering, <b>Darmstadt</b> , <b>Germany</b> .
HONOM 2011	A Discontinuous Galerkin method for Premixed Combustion flow using a Cut- Cell approach, European Workshop on High Order Nonlinear Numerical Meth- ods, <b>Trient, Italy</b> .
FEF 2011	The Cut-Cell DG method, Finite Elements in Fluids conference, Munich, Germany.
CE 2010	A Cut-Cell DG method for Premixed Combustion, International Workshop on Multi-Scale Methods in Computational Engineering, <b>Darmstadt</b> , <b>Germany</b> .
ParCFD 2009	Development of a Discontinuous Galerkin Framework in .NET, Parallel CFD conference, <b>Moffet Field, CA, USA</b> .

## **Co-supervised PhD Thesis**

- Francisco Gutiérrez, M.Sc.: Direct numerical simulation of the droplet evaporation and combustion using a discontinuous Galerkin scheme, ongoing project
- Anne Kikker, M.Sc.: *High-order numerical simulation of oscillating viscoelastic droplet*, ongoing project
- Markus Geisenhofer, M.Sc.: Shock-capturing for high-order discontinuous Galerkin discretizations of compressible flows, ongoing project
- Martin Smuda, M.Sc.: Direct numerical simulation of multi-phase flows using extended Discontinuous Galerkin methods, ongoing project
- Dennis Krause, M.Sc.: Cut cell immersed boundary method for moving body problems, ongoing project
- Thomas Utz, M.Sc.: Level-Set Methods for High-Order DG Schemes, ongoing project
- Kallendorf, C. (2016). An Eulerian Discontinuous Galerkin method for the numerical simulation of interfacial transport. PhD thesis, TU Darmstadt
- Klein, B. (2015). A high-order Discontinuous Galerkin solver for incompressible and low-Mach number flows. PhD thesis, TU Darmstadt

## **Supervised Bachelor- and Master Thesis**

• Beck, L. (2018). Numerical integration over implicitly defined surfaces and volumes. Master's thesis, TU Darmstadt

- Feifel, P. (2018). Polygonale darstellung fluider grenzflächen. Master's thesis, TU Darmstadt
- Degenhardt, M. (2018). Discontinuous Galerkin methods for incompressible flows: 2D turbulence and solver-performance in 3D. Master's thesis, TU Darmstadt
- Lichtenstein, M. (2017). Numerical inverstigation of turbulent puffs. Bachelor's Thesis, TU Darmstadt
- Nietz, F. (2017). Investigation of numerical properties and validation of a discontinuous Galerkin method for multi-phase flows. Master's thesis, TU Darmstadt
- Nguyen, C. (2016). Lie-symmetries in numerical methods. Bachelor's Thesis, TU Darmstadt
- Klein, L. (2016). Lie-symmetries in numerical methods: analysis of the effect of mathematical symmetries on simple partial differential equations. Bachelor's Thesis, TU Darmstadt
- Utz, T. (2014). Validation of curved elements for incompressible, viscous flow problems. Master's thesis, TU Darmstadt
- Keil, M. (2012). Erweiterung und Validierung eines stationären SIMPLE-Lösers für zeitabhängige Probleme. Bachelor's Thesis, TU Darmstadt
- Klein, B. (2011). Implementation of the SIMPLE algorithm for solving the steady incompressible Navier-Stokes equations discretized by the discontinuous Galerkin method. Master's thesis, TU Darmstadt
- Ashoori, R. (2009). Numerical solution of the Navier-Stokes equations using the discontinuous Galerkin method. Master's thesis, TU Darmstadt

## **Teaching experience**

- Applied discontinuous Galerkin methods, lecture with exercises, computational engineering and mechanical engineering program, TU Darmstadt since 2016.
- Advanced research project: comparison of linear solvers for flow-problems with a discontinuous Galerkin discretization, computational engineering program, TU Darmstadt, 2015.
- Tutorial on analysis and numerics in fluid mechanics (Tutorium Analysis und Numerik in der Strömungsmechanik), mechanical engineering program, TU Darmstadt since 2015.
- Exercises for advanced fluid mechanics (Fortgeschrittene Strömungsmechanik), mechanical engineering program, TU Darmstadt, 2011-2012.
- Exercises for Hydraulics B, civil engineering program, TU Darmstadt, 2006/2007.

# Miscellaneous

- Responsibility for IT equipment, including administration of high-performance-computing (HPC) cluster at the chair of fluid dynamics, from 2008 to 2012, includes *supervision of three IT-trainees*.
- Reviewer for SIAM Journal for Scientific Computing.
- Reviewer for International Journal of Computational Fluid Dynamics.
- Reviewer for Computer and Fluids.